Guide to the Boswell Collection Addition
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Financial Papers, 1770-1877; Series IV; 2.0' linear feet (6 boxes)
  - DOUGLAS OF GARALLAN
    - Boswell, Hamilton Douglas
      - Personal estate
        - Settlement of indebtedness to Alexander Boswell, W. S., 1824-33 (Box 23, Folder 650)
        - Memorial and queries for John Douglas Boswell, 1839 Dec 25 (Box 23, Folder 651)
        - Residue account and testament of Jane Douglas Boswell, 1861-66 (Box 23, Folder 652)
        - Offer for assignation of claim against Auchinleck, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 653)
    - Boswell, John Douglas
      - Personal Estate
        - Antenuptial contracts (copies), 1863 (Box 23, Folder 654)
        - Inventories of Garallan, 1863 Oct 24 (Box 23, Folder 655)
        - Residue accounts, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 656)
        - Succession duty receipts, 1863-66 (Box 23, Folder 657)
        - Testament-testamentar, 1863, 1868 (Box 23, Folder 658)
- Personal Papers, 1680-1960; Series V; 0.80' linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series V, Personal Papers, is organized into two subseries: Boswell of Auchinleck Family and Douglas of Garallan Family. Within each, material is arranged chronologically by family generation and then alphabetically by type of material. A small group of articles about the Auchinleck branch is filed at the end of that subseries.
  - BOSWELL OF AUCHINLECK
    - Boswell, Alexander (Lord Auchinleck)
      - Discharge of wages by the wrights and sawyers for Auchinleck House, 1760 Nov 1 (Box 24, Folder 659)
    - Boswell, James
      - Poems (not in the hand of James Boswell), 1790, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 660)
    - Boswell, Sir Alexander
      - Announcement of the laying of the foundation stone of the Ayr court house, printed, 1818 Apr 23 (Box 24, Folder 661)
      - Death notice for Grace (Grizel) Cuming Boswell, 1864 Oct 15 (Box 24, Folder 662)
      - Inventory of the personal estate of George Cuming, Esq. (copies), n.d. (Box 24, Folder 663-664)
      - Marriage contract between Alexander Boswell and Grizel Cuming (registration copy), 1823 Apr 8 (Box 24, Folder 665)
    - General Articles on the Boswells of Auchinleck
      - "An Old Ayrshire Parish in the Forties. Affleck or Auchinleck," by George Eadie, typescript, 1909 Mar (Box 24, Folder 666)
      - "Auchinleck and the Boswells," by James Ferguson, in The Glasgow Herald, 1939 Aug 5
        See: Oversize, Box 29, folder 814
      - "Boswell Resume, Prismatic Speech", by Glenn Coulter, typescripts, inscribed to "the Boswells", 1960 Nov 5 (Box 24, Folder 667)
      - "Auchinleck House and James Boswell," by Robert Metzdorf, typescript (Box 24, Folder 668)
      - Genealogical chart, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 669)
  - DOUGLAS OF GARALLAN
    - Douglas, Hugh
      - Account book, 1680-1700 (Box 24, Folder 670)
      - "Account for the Laird of Garallan-- Garallan's wedding suit", 1719 (Box 24, Folder 671)
      - [Inventory of Katharine Hume's clothes?], n.d. (Box 24, Folder 672)
      - Marriage contract between Hugh Douglas of Garallan and Katharine Hume (copy), 1719 Apr (Box 24, Folder 673)
      - Receipt for regrat bond by John Cannan, 1736 Dec 2 (Box 24, Folder 674)
    - Douglas, Patrick
      - Accounts and receipts, 1782-1805 (Box 24, Folder 675-676)
      - Diploma of the Order of the Beggars' Bennison, 1768 Jun 29 (Box 24, Folder 677)
      - Disposition to Jane Douglas Boswell on 1793 July 10 (registration copy), 1822 Feb 8 (Box 24, Folder 678)
      - Indentures for apprenticeships
        - by John Robertson, 1755 Jul 23
          See: Oversize, Box 29, folder 815
        - by Jeremiah Adderton, 1759 Jun 9
          See: Oversize, Box 29, folder 816
        - by John Ferguson, 1767 Sep 1
          See: Oversize, Box 29, folder 817
        - by George Charles, 1774 Jul 15
          See: Oversize, Box 29, folder 818
      - Marriage contracts
        - Alexander McWilliam and Katherine Neilson, 1775 Sep 16 (Box 24, Folder 679)
        - James McWhirter and Ann Neilson, 1776 Jun 17 (Box 24, Folder 680)
        - Patrick Douglas and Janet Stewart, 1801 Jul 2 (Box 24, Folder 681)
      - Memorandum in the case of the estate of Robert Naismith (Box 24, Folder 682)
      - Minutes of a meeting of the trustees of the high roads in Ayr, printed, 1818 Aug (Box 24, Folder 683)
      - Receipts
        - Books, 1774 Jul (Box 24, Folder 684)
        - Window tax, 1819 (Box 24, Folder 685)
    - Boswell, Hamilton Douglas
      - Accounts, 1815-22, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 686)
      - Bond to Hunters & Co., 1822 Apr 22 (Box 24, Folder 687)
      - Burgess ticket from Kilmarnock, 1805 (Box 24, Folder 688)
      - Commission as Captain in the Ayrshire Rifle Volunteer Battalion, 1805 Aug 15 (Box 24, Folder 689)
      - Discharge by Patrick Douglas to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1839 Feb 7 (Box 24, Folder 690)
      - Extract from the Register of Births showing the children of Hamilton and Jane Douglas Boswell, 1818, 1820 (Box 25, Folder 691)
      - Marriage certificate of Margaret Douglas Boswell and Robert Henderson, 1851 Jul 28 (Box 25, Folder 692)
      - Memorandum of deaths in the family by Jane Douglas Boswell: "This day my mother died...", 1824, 1829 (Box 25, Folder 693)
      - Receipt book of Jane Douglas Boswell, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 694)
    - Boswell, John Douglas
      - 2 ALS from William Dunlop to Mr. Bone concerning the death and funeral of John Douglas Boswell, 1863 Apr (Box 25, Folder 695)
        With: list of "Additional Invitations to funeral," n.d.
      - Ayr Academy annual examination cards, 1822-23 (Box 25, Folder 696)
      - Bond and cautioner in favor of the Commissioners of Supply of Ayr, [1858?] (Box 25, Folder 697)
      - Bond investment with the Caledonian Railway Company, 1856-59 (Box 25, Folder 698)
      - Certificate for John Douglas Boswell as a Writer to the Signet, 1833 Nov 1 (Box 25, Folder 699)
      - Commission as Cornet in the Ayrshire Regiment of Yeomanry Cavalry, 1834 Jul 9 (Box 25, Folder 700)
      - Composition: "The Guerilla Chief", 1828 Apr 15 (Box 25, Folder 701)
      - Discharge and conveyance by Christian Dunlop and others for John Douglas Boswell, 1862 May 14 (Box 25, Folder 702)
      - Glasgow, Paisley Kilmarnock & Ayr Railway Company stock investment, 1847-62 (Box 25, Folder 703)
      - Marriage certificate for John Douglas Boswell and Christina Hamilton, 1842 Jun 6 (Box 25, Folder 704)
      - Membership certificate for the Glasgow Ayrshire Society, 1841 Jan 25 (Box 25, Folder 705)
      - Memorandum book, 1798-99 (Box 25, Folder 706)
      - Passport for France, 1825
        See: Oversize, Box 29, folder 819
      - Petition of Christina Hamilton to to the Pay Office for the pension of Col. William Hamilton, formerly of the Royal North Carolina Volunteers, 1834 (Box 25, Folder 707-709)
      - Trust disposition and settlement by Christina Douglas Boswell, with later codicils, 1883 Nov 28 (Box 25, Folder 710)
    - Boswell, Patrick Charles Douglas
      - ALS from C. Douglas Boswell and ? Boswell to "Willie", 1870 Jan 13 (Box 25, Folder 711)
      - "Account of Expenditure..." (in pounds and rupees), 1880 Jan (Box 25, Folder 712)
      - Copy letter concerning claims of Mr. Henderson on estate, 1870 Jan 8 (Box 25, Folder 713)
      - Journal of trip to North America by John Douglas Boswell, typescript, 1894 (Box 25, Folder 714)
    - Miscellaneous Genealogical Material
      - 2 ALS from James Cummyng of the Lord Lyon's office to Matthew Dickie concerning the descent of the Douglas of Garallan family, 1787 Apr (Box 25, Folder 715)
      - Copy of the coat of arms of Hugh Douglas, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 716)
      - "Douglass or Douglass of Gasallan or Garrallan in Virginia" and "Douglass or Douglass of Gasallan or Garrallan in Scotland;" typescript notes on family descendants, originally made in 1894 (Box 25, Folder 717)
      - Genealogical table, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 718)
- Additional Papers, 1653-1874; Series VI; 0.8 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series VI, Additional Papers, is organized into two subseries: Other Boswells and Other Papers. Other Boswells is organized alphabetically by individual and then by type of material. Other Papers is organized alphabetically by type of material.
  - OTHER BOSWELLS
    - Boswell, David, of Leith
      - Correspondence
        - ALS from Charles Boswell to Mrs. Dalrymple, 1789 May 19 (Box 26, Folder 719)
        - Bill of exchange for Agnes Dalrymple, with ALS from [John?] Mitchell, 1815 Mar 4 (Box 26, Folder 720)
        - Disposition and settlement between Hugh Dalrymple and Agnes Boswell, 1796 Jul 27 (Box 26, Folder 721)
        - Disposition and settlement by David Boswell to Agnes Boswell, 1806 Jun 26 (Box 26, Folder 722)
      - Military commissions for Hugh Dalrymple
        - Ensign in the Bredalbane regiment, 1796 Apr 25 (Box 26, Folder 723)
        - Lieutenant in the Lanark militia, 1803 Sep 3 (Box 26, Folder 724)
        - Ensign in the 6th Garrison battalion, 1808 Jun 16 (Box 26, Folder 725)
        - Lieutenant in the 4th Royal Veterans' battalion, 1813 Sep 9 (Box 26, Folder 726)
    - Boswell, John, of Barglachan
      - Inventory and appraisement of Barglachan, 1841 Jun 5 (Box 26, Folder 727)
      - Settlement of property by John Boswell, 1841 May 11 (Box 26, Folder 728)
    - Boswell, John of Knockroon
      - Burgess ticket for Prestick, 1785 Jun 11 (Box 26, Folder 729)
      - Correspondence
        - Boswell, Charles to John Boswell, 1781 Jul 16 (Box 26, Folder 730)
        - Cochran, William and Patrick, John to John Boswell of Knockroon, 1771 Apr 19 (Box 26, Folder 731)
        - Hamilton, [John?] to John Boswell, 1799 Dec 22 (Box 26, Folder 732)
        - Maule, William to John Boswell, 1796 Sep 29 (Box 26, Folder 733)
        - McCormick, Edward to John Boswell, 1795 May 25 (Box 26, Folder 734)
          With: ALS by McCormick to "My Lords and Gents," 1795 May 25 With: ALS by Alex Fairlie to John Boswell, 1795 May 16
      - Progress of the writs of Knockroon
        - Regrat bond between William Boswell of Knockroon and Hugh Montogmerie of Boigend, 1699 Jun 6 (Box 26, Folder 735)
        - Horning and poinding by Boswell against Montgomerie, 1699 Jun 6 (Box 26, Folder 736-737)
        - Bond between William Boswell and Hugh Montgomerie, 1699 Sep 8 (Box 26, Folder 738)
        - Act for Agnes Boswell against the earl of Loudoun in the matter of the Montgomerie debt, 1725 Dec 2 (Box 26, Folder 739)
        - Deposition of Hugh, earl of Loudoun, 1726 Feb 4 (Box 26, Folder 740)
        - Disposition by Margaret Ferguson and John Boswell of Knockroon to their children, [1738 Nov 11?] (Box 26, Folder 741)
        - Disposition and assignation by Margaret Ferguson to Margaret Ferguson and John Boswell, 1762 Nov 8 (Box 26, Folder 742)
        - Sasine in favor of Margaret Ferguson in liferent and John Boswell in fee, 1767 Jun 10 (Box 26, Folder 743)
        - State of the debts on Knockroon, 1791 May 10 (Box 26, Folder 744)
        - Land and rental papers, 1824-34 (Box 26, Folder 745-747)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Correspondence
      - Charles, James to "My dear Sir", 1837 Jul 12 (Box 26, Folder 748)
      - Cochrane, Charles to "Reverend Sir", 1734 Nov 4 (Box 26, Folder 749)
      - McCormick, Edward to David Limond, 1795 May 25 (Box 26, Folder 750)
      - McCracken, William to Mr. Howatson (printed form letter), 1875 May 8 (Box 26, Folder 751)
      - MacDonald, Daniel to Mrs. Campbell of Skipness, 1775 Sep 27 (Box 26, Folder 752)
    - Land records
      - Cartulary of Paisley: extract copy, 1843 (Box 26, Folder 753)
      - Disposition of ? by William Charton, 1682 (Box 26, Folder 754)
      - Instrument of sasine for John Blackwood of Airsgreen of Airsgreen, 1781 Dec 24 (Box 26, Folder 755)
      - Instrument of sasine for the Cashier for Messrs. Hunters & Co. for various properties and rents, 1781 Aug 15 (Box 26, Folder 756)
      - Instrument of sasine for Helen Crawford and Thomas Cubbison of the smithy and land in Newtown upon Ayr, 1792 Oct 18 (Box 26, Folder 757)
      - "List of the highest Proprietors in Ayrshire with the amounts of their valuations", [ca.1830] (Box 27, Folder 758)
      - Special retour for Mary and Jean Kelso of the lands of Warrockshill or Harrockshill, 1764 Mar 6 (Box 27, Folder 759)
    - Memorabilia
      - Bookplate of Margaret Christina Douglas Boswell (with block), n.d. (Box 27, Folder 760)
      - Pencil sketches, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 761)
      - Seal of the Beggars' Bennison (in case), n.d. (Box 27, Folder 762)
    - Personal Papers
      - Account for Thomas Hamilton, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 763)
      - Address of Alexander Oswald to the Electors of Ayrshire, 1851 Jun 17 (Box 27, Folder 764)
      - Assignation by John Key to Margaret Campbell, 1749 Feb 2 (Box 27, Folder 765)
      - Bill for and protest against Thomas Aikene by Patrick Hume, 1720 (Box 27, Folder 766)
      - Commonplace book, [ca. 1780-1830] (Box 27, Folder 767)
        Includes partial draft of a story, two poems, and biographical sketches of "female worthies"
      - Discharge obligation Hugh Dunbar for Hugh McCowan, 1677 May ? (Box 27, Folder 768)
      - Indenture by Hugh Neilson to David Mitchell as apprentice Merchant Shopkeeper, 1766 Jun 3 (Box 27, Folder 769)
      - Inventory of the effects of John? Craufurd of Crontary, [ca. 1600-50] (Box 27, Folder 770)
      - "Minute of Objection for James Miller, Pannel accused of murder", 1835 Apr 14 (Box 27, Folder 771)
      - Probate of the will of Mrs. Janet Lindsay, 1843 Jan 17 (Box 27, Folder 772)
      - "The Rise and Succession of the familie of Home" (Box 27, Folder 773)
      - Ruling by Parliament in the case of Donald Richmond against the proprietors of Cummock parish, 1653 Dec 21
        See: Oversize, Box 29, folder 820
      - "Sir John Rae Reid Journal", 1833 May 31 (Box 27, Folder 774)
        Mock news sheet concerning the Stepney Green area
    - Poetry
      - "Alonzo the Brave, and the Fair Imogen", 1838? (Box 27, Folder 775)
        Written on the verso of an announcement of the Royal Caledonian Hunt
      - "[Lions?] nigh the stroke of midnight hour", n.d. (Box 27, Folder 776)
    - Printed
      - Announcement of the death of George III, 1820 Feb 2 (Box 27, Folder 777)
      - The Air Advertiser, or, West Country Journal, 1835 Nov 12
        See: Oversize, Box 29, folder 821
      - The Ayr Observer, 1835 Nov 10
        See: Oversize, zbox 29, folder 822
      - Edinburgh Advertiser, 1798 Oct 12 (Box 27, Folder 778)
        Clippings concerning the Battle of the Nile (fragments)
      - "Fiars Prices for the County of Ayr from 1658 to 1821 inclusive", 1822 (Box 27, Folder 779)
      - "Grand Exhibition of the New Heathen Mythology at the Pantheon, Opened Saturday, December the 16th, 1820...", 1820 Dec?
        - Satiric broadside
          See: Oversize, Box 29, folder 823
      - The Graphic: "The Great Tichborne Case" (incomplete), 1874 Feb 28?
        See: Oversize, Box 29, folder 824
      - "Inventory of the Personal Estate of A. B., Merchant in Edinburgh...", 1819 (Box 27, Folder 780)
      - "Plan of Mr. Macindoe's Ball, in the Theatre, Ayr, Friday 1st July 1831" (Box 27, Folder 781)
      - "Reports of Surveys Made for... a Tunnel under the River Forth, at or near Queensbury", 1806 (Box 27, Folder 782)
        With map of proposed tunnel.
    - Unidentified and miscellaneous
      - Receipts, 1675-1741 (Box 27, Folder 783)
      - Unidentified legal document, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 784)
      - Wrappers and labels (Box 27, Folder 785)
        Some annotated.
- Oversize, 4.0' linear feet (2 boxes)
  Oversize items from the previous six series have been arranged here in series order.
  - ESTATE PAPERS
    - "Andrew Gibb. Account with Sir William Forbes, Bart., Executor of the late James Boswell, Esq.", 1795 (Box 28, Folder 786)
    - "View of the Produce of the Estate of Auchinleck, Entailed and Unentailed, for 1818, 1819, 1820, & 1821 and of the Produce expected for 1822" (Box 28, Folder 787)
    - "Farms to Let on the Estate of Auchinleck...", 1823 Nov 20 (Box 28, Folder 788)
    - Rentals of the unentailed estate, 1822-33 (Box 28, Folder 789)
    - Accounts for the unentailed estate, 1822-28 (Box 28, Folder 790-91)
    - Factory accounts (Box 28, Folder 792)
    - Particulars of the Drainage of Auchinleck (Box 28, Folder 793)
    - "Advertisement of Ochiltree Estate", 1834 Aug 2 (Box 28, Folder 794)
    - "Rental of Ochiltree Feus with Terms and Conditions of Tacks" (Box 28, Folder 795)
  - LAND RECORDS: GARALLAN FAMILY
    - "Sketch of the Lands of South Boag [Boig] lying in the Parish of Newg Cummock", 1817 Aug 2 (Box 28, Folder 796)
      See: Oversize, bsd
    - Information concerning the progress of the writs of Garallan, 1821 (Box 28, Folder 797)
    - Section of Strata near New Cumnock Commencing at the Gas Coal, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 798)
    - Valuation of the stock and teinds of the lands within the Parish of Cummock (Box 28, Folder 799)
    - Scheme of the proven rental of the parish of Old Cummock, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 800)
    - Disposition and assignation by David Watson to William Crawford, 1792 Aug 31 (Box 29, Folder 801)
  - FINANCIAL PAPERS
    - Sir James Boswell's Proposal to the Personal Creditors of the late Sir Alexander Boswell, 1828 (Box 29, Folder 802)
    - Life insurance policy of Sir Alexander Boswell, 1819 Jul 2 (Box bsd, folder 803)
      Stored in: broadside.
    - State of interest due on debts secured on the Ochiltree estate, 1835 (Box 29, Folder 804)
    - Rental on Ochiltree lands unsold in the Stirling sale, 1835 (Box 29, Folder 805)
      Also stored in: broadside, 805a.
    - Rental on Ochiltree lands unsold in the Stirling sale, 1835, 1837 (Box bsd, folder 805a)
    - State of the Intromissions and Final scheme of division of the funds, 1876 May (Box 29, Folder 806)
    - "Administration of the goods...left unadministered...", 1834 Apr 23 (Box 29, Folder 807)
    - Power of attorney from Charles Douglas to Patrick Douglas, 1813 Jul 28 (Box 29, Folder 808)
    - Power of attorney from Charles Douglas to Patrick Douglas, 1814 Mar 10 (Box 29, Folder 809)
    - Circular letter, signed "A Partner," warning against the committee's plan to bring actions against partners, [1779?] (Box 29, Folder 810)
    - Lists of debts of Douglas, Heron & Co. to be sold at roup, 1788-1805 (Box 29, Folder 811)
    - Minutes of a meeting of the partners of Douglas, Heron & Co., 1793 (Box 29, Folder 812)
    - Balance sheet for Douglas, Heron & Co., 1804 (Box 29, Folder 813)
  - PERSONAL PAPERS
    - "Auchinleck and the Boswells," by James Ferguson, in The Glasgow Herald, 1939 Aug 5 (Box 29, Folder 814)
    - Indentures for apprenticeships
      - by John Robertson, 1755 Jul 23 (Box 29, Folder 815)
      - by Jeremiah Adderton, 1759 Jun 9 (Box 29, Folder 816)
      - by John Ferguson, 1767 Sep 1 (Box 29, Folder 817)
      - by George Charles, 1774 Jul 15 (Box 29, Folder 818)
    - Passport for France, 1825 (Box 29, Folder 819)
  - ADDITIONAL PAPERS
    - Ruling by Parliament in the case of Donald Richmond against the proprietors of Cummock parish, 1653 Dec 21 (Box 29, Folder 820)
    - Air Advertiser, 1835 Nov 12 (Box 29, Folder 821)
    - Ayr Observer, 1835 Nov 10 (Box 29, Folder 822)
    - "Grand Exhibition of the New Heathen Mythology at the Pantheon, Opened Saturday, December the 16th, 1820...", 1820 Dec? (Box 29, Folder 823)
    - The Graphic: "The Great Tichborne Case" (incomplete), 1874 Feb 28? (Box 29, Folder 824)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 28 (Box 30, Folder 825)
  - Box 1, folder 37 (Box 30, Folder 826)
  - Box 3, folder 114 (Box 30, Folder 827)
  - Box 3, folder 120 (Box 30, Folder 828)
  - Box 3, folder 122 (Box 30, Folder 829)
  - Box 3, folder 123 (Box 30, Folder 830)
  - Box 3, folder 124 (Box 30, Folder 831)
  - Box 5, folder 128 (Box 30, Folder 832)
  - Box 9, folder 293 (Box 30, Folder 833)
  - Box 13, folder 381 (Box 30, Folder 834)
  - Box 13, folder 383 (Box 30, Folder 835)
  - Box 13, folder 388 (Box 30, Folder 836)
  - Box 13, folder 397 (Box 30, Folder 837)
  - Box 15, folder 438 (Box 30, Folder 838)
  - Box 17, folder 489 (Box 30, Folder 839)
  - Box 17, folder 491 (Box 30, Folder 840)
  - Box 17, folder 495 (Box 30, Folder 841)
  - Box 17, folder 497 (Box 30, Folder 842)
  - Box 17, folder 509 (Box 30, Folder 843)
  - Box 17, folder 510 (Box 30, Folder 844)
  - Box 17, folder 511 (Box 30, Folder 845)
  - Box 17, folder 514 (Box 30, Folder 846)
  - Box 17, folder 516 (Box 30, Folder 847)
  - Box 22, folder 631 (Box 30, Folder 848)
  - Box 22, folder 636 (Box 30, Folder 849)
  - Box 24, folder 660 (Box 30, Folder 850)
  - Box 24, folder 681 (Box 30, Folder 851)
  - Box 26, folder 737 (Box 30, Folder 852)
  - Box 27, folder 765 (Box 30, Folder 853)